For the last part of this exercise
series we move away from CodeWorld to
regular Haskell programming.
And the first question probably is how do we
interactively check what our program does.
In this case, we don't have a nice
run button like with CodeWorld.
So if we have a task like this, how do
we actually, how do we work with this?
And the answer is we use ghci to load this file.
And see what the actual values in it are
or play around with functions later on.
So how do we do this?
Well, the basic way is to use a command
prompt and load the file like this.
It then loads your file.
And if I now type in a name from
this file, for example, "c".
I can see that is actually the
constant that is defined here.
If I type in "list", I will get an error
because "list" is undefined and trying to
evaluate undefined results in a runtime error.
Okay, now ghci also checks if
I made a mistake in my program.
Let's say I have a syntax error.
You can already see my editors
also highlighting errors.
So if I type ":r", you can reload the file and
now ghci is telling me that there's an error.
In this case, it's a parse error. Could
have been a type error or what have you.
Let's put the "undefined" back in and
reload the file, and everything works fine.
Now in ghci, you can also
evaluate expressions on their own.
So we don't have to write them into the
into our solution to test something out.
For example, let's
just evaluate this.
What is our set of two-digit numbers?
Here we can just type in a list expression
for this, and ghci will evaluate this.
And you can use all kinds of Haskell
functions to test something out in ghci.
Okay, now let's start with the task!
We should build a list comprehension here that
produces a list of pairs of x and y,
such that x and y are c-digit numbers.
c is defined here as this
constant, and y is at least
twice as big as x, and the sum of
x and y is also a c-digit number.
And as I also already evaluated here, for example,
this set of two-digit numbers is [10..99].
Obviously, one-digit numbers would be [1..9].
The three-digit numbers are then
[100..999], and these are a lot.
Okay, so how do we start?
Well, list comprehensions have this left-hand
side, and this dash, and a right-hand side.
And I'm using these underscores here
which are specially treated by Haskell.
They're called holes, and you can use them to
see what type Haskell is expecting at some point.
If I load them in ghci now...
- I need to save the file, load them here -
It tells me that it found a hole, and
the type of the hole is a pair of two
Integers, which is the first thing here.
Then it says it found a hole of
type Bool, so some condition here.
So we should fill in pairs here, let's call
them "x" and "y", like in the task description.
Now, "x" and "y", as my editor
complains, are not in scope.
So I need to define them somewhere.
This is where the generators in
list comprehensions come from.
Let's say I draw x and y from these two things.
I don't know what they are yet.
Then I again load this file
and now can again see that
Haskell is expecting two lists of
Integers in place of these holes.
I really like using these
holes to incrementally work with programs
and build them up in small steps.
You cannot evaluate them, but
that's okay for the moment.
So what are x and y in this case?
Well, let's take the first condition of x and y.
x and y are c-digit numbers.
Let's fix c to 3 for the moment.
What are all three-digit numbers?
Well, all three-digit numbers, as we
just did in ghci, are [100..999],
and let's do the same thing here.
Okay, now we have gotten rid of all the
holes, so let's see what this list is.
It's a very long list, and ghci does
take some time to actually print it out.
I hit "ctrl-c" to interrupt this.
We want to just look at a small fraction,
we can use the take function and maybe
look at the first 20 elements - like this.
And we see that we have all these pairs, for
example, we have everything starting with 100
and then for y we take all from 100 onwards to
999, and so on, and then for 101 and so on.
Okay, but this is not the only condition; we
also have that y is at least twice as big as x.
So actually, y does not start with 100 but it
always starts with the value twice as big as x.
We can just use the starting value, not of
100 here, but actually make it depend on x
so now we have 2 * x here.
If we reload the file and again take a look at the
first 20 elements, we will see that now instead of
(100,100), the first element, for example,
is (100,200), and then we have (100,201).
Okay, now here's the third condition
that our list has to fulfill:
And this is that the sum of x
and y is also a c-digit number.
In our case, we are just going
with three for the moment.
So what does it mean for x+y to
also be a three-digit number?
Well, the simplest condition here is that
it's just a number smaller than 1000.
So it's at most 999.
And we don't need to check the
lower bound actually, because
just by adding it, we can never drop out
of this range to the left or towards zero.
Okay, then you can obviously just
reload this and take a look.
So the first 20 elements - well these are the
same because this holds for all these elements.
But if we make c smaller in a second, or
parameterize by c, we'll see that actually
there are now fewer elements in this list.
Okay, so now this is our comprehension for c=3.
But, we should make it so
that we can change this c,
and it automatically changes
the list to what we want.
How do we do this?
We need to figure out how one of these 100,
999, and 1000 actually correspond to the c.
Let's do this in small steps; well,
100 = 10^2 and 999 = (10^3)-1
and 1000 = 10^3.
Remember, this is the case for c = 3 so,
everywhere there's a three we can put in the c.
And the 2 obviously is c - 1.
And that's it.
So reload the list.
Take a look, it's still the same
first elements, but now if I
change this to 2 - reload this -
these are now different elements.
And let's choose c = 1; now we can
probably take a look at the whole list.
And we see that we have all the values
that we can add up to still get a one-digit
number where the second number is
at least twice as big as the first.
It goes all the way up to
3 + 6 which is 9 and then
any increase here would mean that
we drop out of this condition.
This is how we solve this.
There are some other things you can do - some
minor differences - but basically, this is the
standard solution, I would say.
You could actually go ahead and say:
"I'm always including the full range for y and
then add a filter here that says that y >= 2 * x."
This would also work.
But it behaves slightly differently
because it will generate all these pairs
with the full range and then filter out the
ones that are not matching this criterion,
while when you write 2 * x here it
will only generate starting from 2 * x.
So you will have fewer checks performed
here but semantically there's no difference.